A Guide to the Randolph-Meikleham Family Papers, 1792-1882
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Randolph-Meikleham Family Papers 1792-1882
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
4726-a
This collection consists of 183 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Randolph-Meikleham Family Papers were loaned to the University of Virginia Library by the Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation, 1954 May 26.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1820-1882, chiefly of Septimia Randolph Meikleham, include correspondence concerning Monticello, Edgehill, the University of Virginia, family matters, social life in Virginia, Boston, Mass., and Washington, D.C., her schoolmates in Cambridge, Mass., travel in Baltimore, Philadelphia, and New York, courtship, and fashion; narratives about the Lewis and Clark expeditions, Monticello, and James and Dolley Madison; legal papers; and poetry.
The papers also contain miscellaneous correspondence, 1836-1839, of the Randolph, Meikleham, Coolidge, and Bankhead families, concerning family and social matters, travelling to Havana, Cuba, and a trip to Philadelphia, Pa., during which Martha Jefferson Randolph sat for a portrait by Thomas Sully; and three letters, 1840-1844, from Dolley Madison to Septimia Randolph Meikleham relating to social and family matters, and specifically Meikleham's marriage.
Of particular note are letters from Meriwether Lewis Randolph concerning life in the frontier town of Little Rock, Ark., including fighting off wolves; a letter, 28 August 1825, from John Hemings, a slave, to Septimia Randolph pertaining to the grounds at Poplar Forest; a letter, ca. 1829, from Martha Jefferson Randolph, Lynchburg, Va., to Septimia Randolph, Edgehill, Va., providing an account of her trip to Lynchburg, sewing; and a letter from George Wythe Randolph, 1860 October 14, speculating on the effect of Lincoln's election on the South.
There is also a letter, 1843 October 2, from Edward Everett, London, Eng., involving the "Cary estate" and his admiration for Thomas Jefferson; and a letter, 30 January 1878, from Charles Stewart Parnell, Rathdrum, Ireland, to Septimia Randolph Meikleham, concerning his mother's visit to the United States.
Of particular interest are a letter, 1792 November 2, from Thomas Jefferson to Thomas Mann Randolph, concerning family matters and Virginia politics and mentioning Madison and Monroe; a letter, 1820 April 17, from John St. George Randolph, Amelia County, Va., to Thomas Mann Randolph, Richmond, Va., on the dismissal of an overseer; and a list, ca. 1821, in Thomas Jefferson's hand, of slaves' bread distribution.
A letter from Archibald Cary at the University of Virginia, to Septimia Randolph, 1834 Dec. 15, mentions that her "acquaintance A. F. E. Robertson (the young man you saw at Davis' & thought so handsome) was shot in the back by an old fellow, while endeavoring to take a dead negro for our anatomical dissections."
Additional items include drafts of poems by Septimia Randolph, and Mrs. Hemans, fragments of Cornelia Randolph's music, and a photograph of an unidentified family home.
Contents List
- John St. George Randolph to Thomas Mann Randolph, 1820 April 17, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Asking that a former overseer, James Linsey, be removed from his property.
- Ellen Bankhead [Carter] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1820 May 18, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Desiring to see Septimia so they could play together in her "baby house."
- John Hemmings [sic], Poplar Forest to "miss Septima monticello" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1825 August 28, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Hemings, a slave, has received Septimia Randolph's letter and is "embreasit" [embarrassed] that she had to write to him. He thanks her for letting him know how her "grand Paw" [Thomas Jefferson] is and is glad "to hear that he is no worst." Hemings hopes that she is well and asks her to "giv my Love to all your brothers Gorg with Randolph [George Wythe Randolph] speculy [specially]." Work continues on the house and the terraces. Hemings hopes "I Shol be able to Com home by the 25 of November Ef Life Last."
- V[irginia] J[efferson Randolph] Trist to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1826 December 24, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with partial address on verso; with partial wax seal. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Mentions her brothers Benjamin [Franklin Randolph], George [Wythe Randolph], and Lewis [Randolph], and sister Ellen [Wayles Coolidge]. Discussing her long silence, the marriage of Mr. Long and Mrs. Selden, and the dismissal of "Mr. Grey, the hotel keeper at the University for bad conduct." Additionally, discusses problems at the University of Virginia resulting in a "prescribed uniform for the students," including "shoes and garters instead of boots, for it was discovered that the young men used their boots to smuggle in liquor into their dormitories." The letter also contains an anecdote about one student purchasing twenty-seven broadcloth coats to pay off his gambling debts.
- M[ary] J[efferson] R[andolph] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1827 June 18, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; with partial wax seal; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, June 21. (Box-folder 1:5)
  Concerning Septimia and George's progress in study, and various illnesses at home. Also, mentions visiting Monticello often where the servants ask about Septimia and George. In a continuation to her mother, Mary discusses the prisoner Quatremere Disjonval's use of spiders to predict the weather, and his eventual rescue by the French from a prison in Utrecht, [Holland].
- E[llen] M. B[ankhead Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1827 September 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l; with attached address leaf; with wax seal. (Box-folder 1:6)
  Mentions not being able to "bear the idea of parting with Dear Willie, and nothing reconciles [her] to it, but knowing how much [she] shall profit by it." Willie is recovering from poor health "which [Ellen] expect[s], has been the cause of his backwardness." She inquires after Aunt Ellen [Wayles Randolph Coolidge]'s child, and asks to know her name.
- E[llen] M. [Bankhead Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1828 January 19, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; with partial wax seal; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, January 22. (Box-folder 1:7)
  Cannot write a long letter "as it is Sally's? washing day." Refers to Willie's interruptions, and his and Martha's mutilation of their toys. Mentions that "Mrs. Trist is very cross, she boxes Uncle Lewis's [Lewis Randolph] ears two or three times every day, and once boxed Uncle Trist [Nicholas P. Trist] for preventing her from giving an Apple to Martha."
- E[llen] M. B[ankhead Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1828 March 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; with partial wax seal; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, March. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Concerning her progress in school.
- Lewis [Randolph] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1828 March 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; with partial wax seal; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, March 18. (Box-folder 1:9)
  Discussing the progress of the children Willie, Martha and Maria.
- Ellen M. Bankhead [Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1828 November 24, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; with wax seal. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Mentions Aunt Virginia [Jefferson Randolph Trist's] son, and laments Aunt Jane and Uncle Jeff's only having daughters. Discusses Willie's improved behavior, and Uncle [Nicholas P.] Trist's clerkship in Washington.
- Ellen M. Bankhead [Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1828 December 21, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; with wax seal. (Box-folder 1:11)
  Relating her trip on a Steamboat, and Willie's recovery from a cold.
- Phoebe Ann Foxcroft to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1829 January 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. (Box-folder 1:12)
  Concerning the affairs at Septimia's former school, and of Cambridge, Massachusetts. Mentions enclosing a lock of her hair, and asks for one in return.
- Ellen M. Bankhead [Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia] Randolph, 1829 January 16, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; with partial wax seal. (Box-folder 1:13)
  Asks if the report of "Old Mrs. Trist's" death is true, inquires about her schooling, and relates an anecdote about her traveling to a wedding on an ox cart.
- Ellen M. Bankhead [Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1829 January 31, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; with wax seal. (Box-folder 1:14)
  Chastising Septimia for not answering her questions, especially hers concerning the death of Mrs. Trist. Mentions that she does not find Willie "a very comfortable bedfellow, for he very often rains all over [her]."
- Ellen M. Bankhead [Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1829 February 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l; with attached address leaf; with wax seal. (Box-folder 1:15)
  Asks if her father [Thomas Mann Randolph] and brother John are alive or dead because she has not heard from them. She worries about them and Uncle William because of "their being so near the University whilst that dreadful fever is raging there."
- Ellen M. Bankhead [Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1829 April 12, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; with wax seal. (Box-folder 1:16)
  Says that she must say something "about my darling spoiled Willie," and that he yet is fond of playing with babies as a little girl. She also mentions Tom's learning to shoot, and his fondness for his gun. Also contains a drawing by "little Willie" for little Pat.
- Ellen Coolidge to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1829 April 16, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; with wax seal; postmarked Boston, MA, April 17. (Box-folder 1:17)
  Providing Septimia with news of Ellen's children, including Septimia's "favorite" Ellen. Mentions John Rogers', who had married Miss Ellen Derby, loss of fortune. Provides her with several fashion tips, and encourages her studies, but claims that she "will a few years hence, find a ready use of [her] needle, and a competent knowledge of housekeeping of more value, of more absolute necessity, than [she] can possibly imagine now."
- M[artha Jefferson] R[andolph] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], [1829 June 7]? Sunday Morning, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; with wax seal; postmarked Lynchburg, VA, June 8. (Box-folder 1:18)
  Describes a brief stop to Mr. Davis' house, the condition of Jane Randolph, and her inability to see anyone without "a reinforcement to [her] wardrobe."
- E[llen] M. [Bankhead Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1829 September 20, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address. Letter torn along old fold and brittle along others. (Box-folder 1:19)
  Describes a visit with Mrs. Buckner and Mrs. Minor and their families, and the intelligence of their daughters. Mentions preparations for Miss Dorothea [Minor's] impending wedding. In a continuation of the letter on the 21st, Bankhead says that she is interested in the "secret" Septimia has to tell her, but that she can guess what it is.
- Ann and Jane Higginbotham to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1829 December 5, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, December 7. (Box-folder 1:20)
  Ann describes teasing Susan Johnson for her secret engagement, and mentions that Elizabeth and Mary Winn are to go to the Richmond "debates" in the convention. Jane's continuation tells her to give her love to Ellen Bankhead [Carter] who is now with Septimia in Washington, and inquires about life in the city.
- Cary Anne N. Randolph and L[ewis] Randolph to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1830 January 12, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso. (Box-folder 1:21)
  Cary Anne discusses life at school, and the arrival of Uncle Lewis [Randolph] and Lucy Minor. Lewis' continuation describes the "Bedlam" qualities of his house at school. Extols Miss Minor's good qualities, and, in a postscript, asks for several books from Monticello.
- Emmeline Foxcroft to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1830 February 17, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso. (Box-folder 1:22)
  Describes changes in Cambridge, including a new president at Harvard, and the parties there. Mentions the arrival of Mr. Davis and his daughter to Cambridge, and their purchase of a house there. She also asks to be remembered by several of Septimia's acquaintances in Cambridge, Mr. Rand, Miss Mary Stearns, Phoebe Anne, and Emmeline's mother.
- Lucia [Swett] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1830 April 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; with partial wax seal. (Box-folder 1:23)
  Concerning various former acquaintances in Boston.
- B[enjamin] F[ranklin] Randolph to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], [1830] May 20, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked University of Virginia, May 21. (Box-folder 1:24)
  Relating the affection between Mr. and Mrs. Dunglison in her illness. Claims that the Virginia Legislature should prohibit Fairs, like the one just ended, within five miles of the University of Virginia because "it is nothing but an assemblage of women to gull the students." He also mentions his appointment as one of the essay writers for the University's "public day."
- E[llen] B[ankhead Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1830 August 30, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; with wax seal; postmarked Charlotttesville, VA, September 3. (Box-folder 1:25)
  Relating family matters, as well as marriage prospects of mutual friends. In a postscript, Ellen asks her Aunt Cornelia [Jefferson Randolph] to add her own postscript in Septimia's next letter, informing her of the current fashions.
- Lucia [Swett] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], [1830] September 21, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Boston, MA, September. (Box-folder 1:26)
  Written in crosshatch, this letter is difficult to read. Thanks Septimia for a gift, and relates the progress of her brothers, one entering divinity school, and the other medicine as well as other family news. She also says, "I still continue with Doctor [John]? Park, and indeed [I think]? I shall for some time to come, and I am delighted both with him and his school, and I hope if you ever should come ou[t] here again, to stay for any length of time, [and] you will go there, we may enjoy it as much as we did; at the time we were together at Miss Spooner's who has been so sick as to be oblidged to go up to Lancaster, and resign her school to Hannah Spooner, and in consequence of this, most of those, with whom we went to school have been [dispersed?], Frances Higginson, Louisa Perkins, and Elizabeth Chapman, are at Mr. [Ralph Waldo?] Emerson's and our friend the latter, appears as friendly and as amiable as ever."
- Ellen B[ankhead Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1831 April 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; with wax seal; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, April 24. (Box-folder 1:27)
  Relates her interaction with Sarah Lewis, and that she has heard from Mr. Shaaf that the Misses Randolph waltz beautifully in Washington. She instructs Septimia not to reveal this in Charlottesville because of a recent outcry against waltzing. She claims that if she returns to Charlottesville, Septimia will drive the students crazy. Ellen also describes her frequent walks to Charlottesville, relates the affairs at Monticello, and lists the engagements of several of their mutual friends.
- E[llen] B[ankhead Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], [ca. 1831] July, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, July 23. (Box-folder 1:28)
  Discusses a visit to Spring Grove, Willie's disposition, and a party that she has attended. At the close of her letter, she laments the dilapidation of Monticello.
- [L. Lear] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1831 September 5, ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:29)
  Asking Septimia to join her for a ride.
- C[ary] A[nne] and M[ary] J[efferson] Randolph to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1831 November 15, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso. (Box-folder 1:30)
  Discussing their grandmother's illness, and the marital status of their University friends.
- Maria C. Harford to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1832 June 19, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Philadelphia, PA, June 18. (Box-folder 1:31)
  Laments not seeing her before her travel to Georgia, and relates an anecdote about a neighbor of hers being serenaded. Discusses her travels to Philadelphia and to New York, but is fearful that her boat will be searched "for fear of the Colera."
- M. S. Randolph to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1832 June 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. (Box-folder 1:32)
  Inquires about cousin Ellen's [Bankhead Carter] marriage, and reveals that their cousin John is engaged.
- B[enjamin] F[ranklin] Randolph to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1832 [July 4], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. (Box-folder 1:33)
  Relates that his endeavors to marry rich have been thwarted, and that doctors cannot marry well because of low pay.
- Ellen [Bankhead] Carter to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1832 July 18, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; with wax seal; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, July 21. (Box-folder 1:34)
  Describes events in Charlemont, and her interactions with her new husband's relations. She also reveals that her brother John is engaged to Elizabeth Christian, who "is not worth a cent," and discusses his financial and employment difficulties.
- L[ewis] Randolph to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1832 July 31, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Charlottesville, VA, August 1. (Box-folder 1:35)
  Describes the condition of himself and Mr. Deveaux upon their return to Edgehill. Reports his visit to Monticello, and laments its dilapidated condition. Lewis proclaims that he would not visit the house because he would not show [James T.] Barclay the respect of calling on him. Lewis goes on further to say, "I most sincerely pray that before I leave the neighborhood my eyes may be gladdened with the sight of the House wrapped in flames, and that every vestige of building may be swept from the top of the Mountain."
- L[ewis] Randolph to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1832 October 7, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. (Box-folder 1:36)
  He anxiously desires to return to Washington because of the lack of friends at Edgehill.
- Ellen Bankhead [Carter] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1832 [ ] 8, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 1:37)
  Hopes that Septimia will travel with her after she sees her.
- Unidentified to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham] [1832]?, AN, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf. (Box-folder 1:38)
  Asks her to send the things he requested, and his desire to meet with Ellen [Bankhead Carter] and Willie when they arrive.
- Matilda [Palmer] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], [1833]? February, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked City of Washington, March 2. (Box-folder 1:39)
  Sorry for Alexandrine's departure after her wedding, and that she needed to assist Frank the morning after her nuptials. Palmer asks Septimia to thank her brother Lewis [Randolph] for the gift of a Newfoundland dog despite its propensity for running away.
- "Dee" [Delia T. Steward Parnell] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1833 July 29, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with separate address leaf. (Box-folder 1:40)
  Letting her know that she is presently in Philadelphia, but will continue her travels soon.
- L[ewis] Randolph to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1833 October 1, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; with wax seal; postmarked City of Washington, October 2. (Box-folder 1:41)
  Announces his arrival to Washington, but claims that where he expected Mr. [Nicholas P.] Trist, "the house was void of white folks," and claims that his "reign" as a "nabob" will be short lived. Relates an anecdote about meeting two drunk acquaintances of Septimia's, Tom Thuston and Hugh Allen. Relates traveling to New York, and meeting with "Old Mrs. Hamilton" there, who is selling her house because Aaron Burr had purchased a farm near hers. He also codedly relates his amorous exploits.
- "Till" [Matilda Palmer] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1833 October 2, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked City of Washington, October 9. (Box-folder 1:42)
  Describes her trip through Charlottesville, her admiration of its and the University's beauty, on her way to the Warm Springs, and her visit there.
- C[ornelia] J[efferson] R[andolph] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1833 October 7, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked City of Washington, October 9. (Box-folder 1:43)
  Concerning the affairs and estates of acquaintances in Washigton, and mentioning an outbreak of fever there. At the close of her letter, Cornelia says that "Richard and Ellen [Bankhead Carter]...interrupted [her] to tell [her] of a fresh piece of roguery of Sally's. She took the key out of Ellen's door and went into the locked closet with it; no one knew before that it would open that door; Ellen caught her there. Richard said he had already given her one whipping while [they] were away for stealing [Septimia's] parasol and hiding it."
- "Till" [Matilda Palmer] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1833 October 23, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; with partial wax seal; postmarked City of Washington, October 29. (Box-folder 1:44)
  Hopes her health will improve by the time Septimia can visit in the Spring. Mentions an encounter with Lewis [Randolph] and Miss Sally Kean, and asks about Septimia's other relatives.
- Matilda [Palmer] and William R. Palmer to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1833 November 3, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked City of Washington, November 12. (Box-folder 1:45)
  Concerning the affection of Septimia's friends in Washington, and hopes to see her in Washington in the winter.
- L[ewis] R[andolph] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1833 November 3, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; with wax seal; postmarked City of Washington, November 5. (Box-folder 1:46)
  Regarding denying a request to read an eleven page letter Septimia had written to "Sall," and that Ann is "smitten sore with [him]." Relates that Hugh Allen's nightly visits to "Sall" has caused her "decaying and [will result in her] sinking into a premature grave." He also relates "a blow up about old clean drinking Jones" between Mrs. Dr. Thomas and Mrs. Forrest, and that "the Dr. and his wife have become very unpopular, she is the most slanderous bitch [he] ever knew and he a dirty intriguing coward."
- Mary [Page Randolph] to "Dear Tim" [Septimia Randolph Meikleham], 1833 November 15, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address on verso; postmarked Norfolk, VA, November 18. (Box-folder 1:47)
  Concerning her arrested travels, and difficulty finding suitable passage. Relates several stories of people she has met with in her travels, and her belief that her "circumstances have made [her] feel old at 22."
- M[ary] J[efferson] R[andolph] to Septimia Randolph [Meikleham], 1833 November 24, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with address; postmarked Boston, MA, November 25. (Box-folder 1:48)